<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Richmond before Queene Elizabeth of famous memorie, vpon the 28. of March, 1596. By the reuerend father in God Anthony Rudd, Doctor in Diuinitie, and Lord Bishop of S. Dauids</title>
            <author>Rudd, Anthony, 1549 or 50-1615.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11162</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21432</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103177</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838934</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838934</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3325</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11162)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3325)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1218:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Richmond before Queene Elizabeth of famous memorie, vpon the 28. of March, 1596. By the reuerend father in God Anthony Rudd, Doctor in Diuinitie, and Lord Bishop of S. Dauids</title>
                  <author>Rudd, Anthony, 1549 or 50-1615.</author>
                  <author>R. S., fl. 1603.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 57, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by R. Field] for Thomas Man,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed: R.S.</note>
                  <note>Some pages cropped at head, affecting page numbers.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3325:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3325:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT RICHMOND BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Queene Elizabeth of famous memorie, vpon the 28. of March, 1596.</p>
            <p>By the reuerend father in God ANTHONY RVDD, Doctor in Diuinitie, and Lord Biſhop of S. Dauids.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Thomas Man.</hi> 1603.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3325:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3325:2"/>
            <head>To all that feare God.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS Sermon bred much ſpeech long ago, and the ſight of it was greatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired by many. But it hath bene concealed theſe ſeuen yeares and more, by him that had the copy therof. Howbeit, now at the laſt it is publiſhed, vpon hope that it may with as good meaning be conſtrued by the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as it was formerly vttered by the Author.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3325:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3325:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSAL. 90. 12.</bibl>
               <q>Teach vs ſo to number our dayes, that we may applie our hearts vnto wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS Pſalme was endi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Moſes</hi> the man of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.</note> God: the occaſion of the making of it grew thus. After that thoſe which were ſent to ſearch the land of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan, were returned fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the viewing or ſurueying of it: vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the report of ſome of them that the inhabitants were Gyants in reſpect of the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, who in compariſon of them ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med but graſhoppers, and that their cities were walled vp to heauen, and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 9. 1.</note> ſo iudged impregnable; the people murmured. Whereupon God ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiated, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 14. 29.</note> that their carkaſſes ſhould
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3325:4"/>
fall in the wilderneſſe, ſo many as were twenty yeares old and vpward. Then, <hi>Moſes</hi> penned this Pſalme, that it might be a monument of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and a forme of prayer for the obtaining of mercy.</p>
            <p>This text, I ſay, is a prayer. And whereas there be foure ſorts of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 1.</note> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned by the Apoſtle: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, firſt a petition for the obtaining of that good which we want &amp; deſire. Secondly deprecation, whereby we requeſt the turning away of that euill from vs, which we feare and haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued. Thirdly interceſſion, when we intreate for others. Fourthly, thankſgiuing for benefits receiued. Now this prayer is a petition: firſt for inſtruction, in theſe words, <hi>Teach vs:</hi> ſecondly in this particular, <hi>to number our dayes:</hi> thirdly to this end, <hi>that we may apply our hearts vnto wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The requeſt of teaching implieth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3325:4"/>
ignorance in the petitioner, and the acknowledging thereof by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. For the ſluggard which is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 26. 16.</note> wiſer in his owne conceipt, then ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen men that can render a reaſon; and al they that be wiſe in their owne <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5. 21.</note> eyes &amp; prudent in their owne ſight, contemne all doctrine and admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hating to be taught and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. Therefore woe vnto them, for there is more hope of fooles then of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 26. 12.</note> them: for fooles ſinne of ignorance, but theſe ſinne of malice.</p>
            <p>I haue learned of <hi>Zophar</hi> the Naamathite, that vaine man would <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 11. 12.</note> be counted wiſe, though (indeed) man new borne, is like a wild Aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colt; that is, without vnderſtanding. So that whatſoeuer good gifts he hath afterward, they come of God, and not of nature. Verily ignorance is the mother not onely of admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, while we wonder at thoſe things whereof we know not the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3325:5"/>
cauſe or reaſon: but alſo of errour. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. 29.</note> For by it men ſpeake good of euill, and euill of good; putting darkneſſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſai.</hi> 5. 20.</note> for light, and light for darkneſſe; bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for ſweet, and ſweete for ſower: being like the children of Nineueh, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ionas</hi> 4. 11.</note> who could not diſcerne betweene their right hand and their left.</p>
            <p>Seeing then the naturall man vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth not the things that are of <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14.</note> the ſpirite of God (for they are foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſſe vnto him<hi>:)</hi> therefore <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codemus</hi> though a maiſter in Iſraell, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3. 1. 2. <hi>&amp;.</hi>
               </note> muſt be Catechiſed before he be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated, and ſee the kingdome of God. If <hi>Saul</hi> heare not <hi>Ananias,</hi> the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 9. 17. 18. <hi>&amp;.</hi>
               </note> ſcales will not fall from the eyes of his mind any more then from the eyes of his body. <hi>Cornelius</hi> the Captaine of the Italian band, muſt heare <hi>Peter</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 10.</note> preach vnto him, and his familie, and his friends, before that he and they receiue the holy Ghoſt. And how ſhould the Eunuch of Aethiopia vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3325:5"/>
what he readeth in <hi>Eſai,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 8. 26. vſque ad finem.</note> 
               <hi>Philip</hi> the Euangeliſt be ioyned to his chariot, and comming vp to ſit with him expound the Scriptures vnto him? Aſſuredly the kingly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet himſelfe, cannot ſee how the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. 17.</note> proſperity of the wicked may ſtand with Gods prouidence, vntill he go into the ſanctuarie of God, there to learne by his word and holy ſpirite, that he ordereth all things moſt wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and iuſtly. And it is put downe in the foote of one of the Pſalmes, that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49. 20.</note> if man be in honour, and vnderſtand not, he is like to beaſts that periſh.</p>
            <p>Wherefore to preuent this daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, <hi>Dauid</hi> had need to haue <hi>Nathan</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24.</note> and <hi>Gad</hi> to admoniſh and aduiſe him. And if <hi>Ahab</hi> had not wanted grace, and abandoned the feare of God from before his eyes; yea and <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 21. 20.</note> ſold himſelfe to worke wickedneſſe in the ſight of the Lord: he might haue receiued great benefit by the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3325:6"/>
godly leſſons of <hi>Elias</hi> and <hi>Micheas.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 21 <hi>&amp;</hi> 22. 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 12. 2.</note> King <hi>Iehoaſh</hi> did that which was good in the ſight of the Lord, all the time that <hi>Iehoiada</hi> the Prieſt taught him. If the Nineuites had not heard <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ionas</hi> 3.</note> &amp; beleeued <hi>Ionas,</hi> they had vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly bene deſtroyed in their ſinnes. And to be ſhort, where propheſying <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 29. 18.</note> faileth, there both the Prince and the people muſt needs periſh in the end.</p>
            <p>Wherfore Almighty God for the ſingular loue which he beareth to mankind, hath furniſhed al ages with skilfull and ſound teachers. For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, before the floud, after <hi>Adam</hi> the monarch of the whole earth (by <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. 3. 4.</note> whoſe inſtructions his ſonnes ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the king of heauen) was <hi>Sheth:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> 26.</note> who taught the men of his time to call vpon the name of God, reſtoring religion (which by the wicked had a long time bene ſuppreſſed.) <hi>Henoch</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 5. 22.</note> likewiſe, that walked with God. <hi>Noe</hi> alſo, whom the Apoſtle entituleth a <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 5:</note>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:3325:6"/>
Preacher of righteouſneſſe. After the floud, till the giuing of the lawe in mount Sinai, for the ſpace of 857 yeares, the Patriarks were the worlds inſtructors: whom in their peram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations from nation to nation, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105. 13. 14. 15.</note> from one kingdome to another peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, God ſuffered not to be wronged, but euen reproued kings for their ſakes, ſaying: Touch not mine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed, and do my Prophets no harme. At the giuing of the law it was ordained, that the Prieſts lippes <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 2. 7.</note> ſhould preſerue knowledge, and that men ſhould ſeeke the lawe at their mouthes, becauſe they are the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of the Lord of hoſts. And when they failed in their ordinarie duty, then God ſtirred vp extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 9. 8 9 10.</note> teachers called Seers, men of God, and Prophets. So that at ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry times and in diuerſe maners God <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 1. 2.</note> ſpake in the old time to our fathers by the Prophets: but in theſe laſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3325:7"/>
dayes he hath ſpoken vnto vs by his ſonne, whom he hath made heire of all things. And when he aſcended vp on high, leading captiuity captiue, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph</hi> 4. 8. 11. 12. 13.</note> he gaue gifts vnto men; euen ſome to be Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets, and ſome Euangeliſts, and ſome pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and teachers: for the gathering together of the Saints, for the worke of the miniſterie, and for the edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the body of Chriſt, till we all meete together in the vnitie of faith, and the knowledge of the ſonne of God vnto a perfect man, and vnto the meaſure of the age of the fulneſſe of Chriſt. And out of this number, are we to expect from time to time, ſome to teach vs rightly to number our dayes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eliphaz</hi> the Temanite by long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 4. 20. 21.</note> diſcreetly noted, that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are deſtroyed from the morning to the euening without regard, and that men of dignitie go to death without
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3325:7"/>
wiſedome: meaning, that we do not commonly marke our owne frailtie pictured in other mens funerals, and that death ſeazeth vpon many of vs, before we do ſo much as thinke of it. And therfore we haue need of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full inſtructors to teach vs to number our dayes.</p>
            <p>The euer liuing God (the number <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 36. 26.</note> of whoſe yeares cannot be ſought out) who doth great things and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 5. 9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9. 10.</note>: yea maruellous things without number: who counteth the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147. 4.</note> number of the ſtars, and calleth them all by their names: neither is there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 25. 3.</note> number to be found in his armies: who likewiſe in his iuſt iudgement <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſai.</hi> 65. 12</note> numbred idolaters to the ſword in <hi>Eſaies</hi> time: and numbred the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi> and finiſhed it <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 5. 26.</note> in the dayes of <hi>Daniel:</hi> with whom <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 14. 5.</note> the number of our moneths &amp; daies is determined, ſo that we cannot paſſe the bounds which he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3325:8"/>
who alſo hath the iuſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of all the haires of our head<hi>:</hi> and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 30.</note> doth hide the number of yeares from <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 15. 20.</note> tyrants: who (I ſay) ſealeth in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head the full number of all that ſhall <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 7. 4. <hi>VViſ.</hi> 11. 17</note> be ſaued: and hath ordered all things in meaſure, number and weight: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen he it is, of whom we deſire to be taught to number our dayes.</p>
            <p>There is to be obſerued in reading of the Scriptures and eccleſiaſticall Hiſtories, a diuine Arithmeticke, or arithmeticall Diuinitie: whereby we may be the better armed in all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters againſt the Romaniſt, the Iew, the Atheiſt, and the tentations of the diuell.</p>
            <p>Againſt the Romaniſt<hi>:</hi> becauſe the man of ſinne is manifeſtly diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, by the true vnderſtanding of the three numerall Characters men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the booke of of the Reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 13. 18</note> For the number of the beaſt is the number of a man, and his num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3325:8"/>
is χξς: that is, 666. which num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber is contained in the ſixe Hebrew Characters, whereby the Latine word <hi>Romanus</hi> is expreſſed:</p>
            <list>
               <item>Ro ר 200</item>
               <item>M מ 40</item>
               <item>A ע 70</item>
               <item>N נ 50</item>
               <item>V ו 6</item>
               <item>S ש 300</item>
            </list>
            <p>And thereby it is implyed, that <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> or a man of Rome, ſhould be the name of Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>Againſt the Iew denying the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias</hi> to be come as yet, we may be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by the right vnderſtanding of <hi>Daniels</hi> 70. weekes: that is, 490. years <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 24. 25.</note> determined to ſeale vp ſins, to bring in euerlaſting righteouſneſſe, and to annoint the moſt holy; reckoning from the ſecond yeare of <hi>Darius No-thus</hi> the king of <hi>Perſia,</hi> vnto the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Ieruſalem, made by <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> in the ſecond yeare of his father <hi>Veſpaſian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againſt the Atheiſt we are the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter prepared, if we haue at our fingers end an exact and perfect ſupputation
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3325:9"/>
of the number of the yeares of the world, from the beginning thereof vntil this preſent time. Namely, from the Creation to <hi>Noës</hi> floud, 1656. yeares: from the floud till <hi>Abrahams</hi> departure out of <hi>Haran</hi> a citie in <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopotamia,</hi> 427. From thence to the giuing of the Lawe in mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> 430. From that time to the building of <hi>Salomons</hi> temple, 480. thenceforth to the captiuitie of <hi>Babylon,</hi> 408. then to their returne home againe, 70. and from their returne to the birth of Chriſt, 457. From the Natiuitie of our Sauiour Chriſt vntill this preſent day, 1595. complete and vpward. But that branch of Arithmeticke, wherby we ſhould make ſupputation of the yeares to come to the end of the world, is cloſed vp in the breſt or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret of the all-ſufficient, and al-know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God. For, of that day and houre knoweth no man, no not the Angels <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 13. 32.</note> which are in heauen, neither the Son
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3325:9"/>
of man himſelfe, ſaue the Father.</p>
            <p>And we ſhall be the better able to ſtand vpright againſt the tentations of the diuell, when we are painefully exerciſed in numbring of our dayes: I meane, not the bare numbring of the years of our life after the account of the Church booke, be they 20, 40, 60, 70, more or leſſe: but in deepely <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 29. 30. 31. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 11. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2. 15. 16. 17. <hi>Ec.</hi> 7. 36.</note> conſidering the ſhortneſſe, frailtie and vncertaintie of this life which is lent vnto vs for the ſetting foorth of Gods glorie in it; and withal, in daily meditating how and which way wee may in euery part of our life beſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite the Church and Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monwealth wherein we liue, ſhewing our ſelues throughout moſt zealous for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancing of Religion and Iuſtice.</p>
            <p>Aſſuredly when I looke backe to the ſeauen liberall ſciences, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider in them as in all other things els <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 1. 14.</note> vnder the Sunne, vanity and vexation of the Spirit: then I conclude in my
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3325:10"/>
priuate meditation, that he is the beſt Grammarian, who committeth no incongruitie in his life, againſt faith, and good manners, but frameth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to ſerue God without feare all <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 1. 74. 75.</note> the dayes of his life, in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe before him: imitating the example of <hi>Zacharie</hi> and <hi>Elizabet</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib. verſ.</hi> 6.</note> who were iuſt before God, and wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in all the commaundements and ordinances of the Lord without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe.</p>
            <p>I eſteeme him the beſt Logician, which bendeth the fiſt againſt impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and iniquitie<hi>:</hi> making ſtrong Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſmes againſt all tentations or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of the world with the pompe thereof, of the fleſh with al her allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and of Sathan with all his ſleights; being armed with the ſhield <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 16. 17</note> of faith, and the ſword of the Spirit, which is the word of God, whereby Sathan may be both repelled and wounded, as appeareth by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3325:10"/>
betweene him and our Sauiour <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. 1. <hi>to the</hi> 12.</note> Chriſt in the Goſpell of <hi>Mathew.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He is in mine opinion, the beſt Rhetorician, who if he be eloquent, is therewithal mightie in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as <hi>Apollos</hi> was: ſpending his elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 18. 24.</note> in Sermons of repentance as did <hi>Iſay,</hi> and in penning of heauenly ditties as <hi>Dauid</hi> did: employing all his elocution in vttering ſuch wordes as be good to the vſe of edifying, that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 29.</note> they may miniſter grace vnto the hearers, becauſe he deſireth to profite <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 1. 4. 5.</note> them rather then to delight them.</p>
            <p>Him do I iudge the beſt Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trician, who ordereth all his doings in meaſure, number and weight, by <note place="margin">
                  <hi>VViſ.</hi> 11. 17</note> the example of God aboue<hi>:</hi> who maketh the word of God the rule <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 9 105.</note> and the ſquire, the line and the leuell of all his actions: who being rooted and grounded in loue, is able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend with all Saints what is the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 3. 18.</note> breadth and length, depth and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3325:11"/>
height (that is, the excellencie and perfection) of the loue of Chriſt, which paſſeth knowledge: being ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded, that neither height nor <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 38. 39.</note> depth, nor farre diſtance, nor any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creature ſhall be able to ſeparate him from the loue of God which is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord.</p>
            <p>I count him the beſt Aſtronomer, who by the view of the hoſt of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, can (Gods ſpirit directing him) <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 20.</note> picke out the eternall power &amp; God-head of the Creator, or his maieſtie and glorie, which reſulteth of his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, wiſedome and goodneſſe; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by taking occaſion to glorifie him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly. Who when he looketh vp to the skie, not onely acknowledgeth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 1.</note> that the heauens declare the glorie of God, and the firmament ſheweth his handiworke: but alſo concludeth in a good conſcience, that as high as the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. 11</note> heauen is aboue the earth, ſo great is his mercie toward them that feare
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3325:11"/>
him. And caſting in his mind the ſundrie Clymates of the world, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolueth by aſſurance of faith, that as farre as the Eaſt is from the Weſt, ſo farre hath God remoued our ſinnes <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib. verſ.</hi> 12.</note> from vs.</p>
            <p>I reckon them the beſt Muſitians, which ſpeake to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in Pſalmes <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 19.</note> and hymnes and ſpirituall ſongs, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging and making a melodie to the Lord in their hearts: whoſe thoughts wordes and deedes are in tune with Gods holy Scriptures, making a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort or harmonie among themſelues without any iarre or diſcord, from <hi>Gammuth</hi> to <hi>Ela,</hi> that is, from the cradle to the graue.</p>
            <p>And vndoubtedly they are the beſt Arithmeticia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, whom God hath taught to number their dayes in ſuch ſort, that they may apply their hearts vnto wiſedome.</p>
            <p>The mind of man is the dwelling place of vnderſtanding: and the heart
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3325:12"/>
of man is the ſeat of the affections. Now it ſufficeth not that the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of goodneſſe be ſwimming or floating in the braine, vnleſſe the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of godlineſſe be ſetled in the heart. For of the aboundance of the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 34.</note> heart the mouth ſpeaketh, either words of edification, whereby thou mayeſt be iuſtified: or euill wordes <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib. ver.</hi> 37. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 33</note> corrupting good manners, whereby thou ſhalt deſerue to be condemned. Out of the heart (I meane the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. 19</note> affection of the heart) proceede thoſe things which defile the man; as euill thoughts, murders, adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, fornications, thefts, falſe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, ſlaunders: and therefore no maruel if the floud drowned them of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. 5.</note> the old world, becauſe all the imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of their hearts were onely e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil continually. Yea let <hi>Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 8. 20. 21.</note> with his money periſh, hauing neither part nor fellowſhip in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall buſineſſe, becauſe his hart
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3325:12"/>
was not right in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>But on the other ſide, the end of the commaundement is loue out of <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 5.</note> a pure heart, and of a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and of faith vnfained. Therefore bleſſed are the pure in heart, for they <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 8.</note> ſhall ſee God. The ſeede which fell in good ground, are they which with <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 8. 15. <hi>Act.</hi> 15. 9.</note> an honeſt and good heart, purifyed by faith, heare the word and keepe it, and bring forth fruite with patience. Be glad then ye righteous, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. 11</note> in the Lord, and be ioyfull all ye that are vpright in heart, applying it wholly vnto wiſedome.</p>
            <p>Now if it be demaunded what true wiſedome is, it may out of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> be briefly defined, The vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and obſeruing of Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements. For theſe be the wordes of <hi>Moſes</hi> in his exhortation <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deu.</hi> 4. 5. 6.</note> to the people: Behold I haue taught you ordinances and lawes, as the Lord my God commaunded me.
<pb facs="tcp:3325:13"/>
Keepe them therefore and do them: for that is your wiſedome, and your vnderſtanding in the ſight of the people, which ſhall heare all theſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and ſhall ſay: Onely this people is wiſe, and of vnderſtanding: yea God himſelfe vttereth in <hi>Iob,</hi> words of the ſame meaning, ſaying vnto man: Behold, the feare of the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 28. 28.</note> Lord is wiſdome; and to depart from euill, is vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, though a man were as well experienced and worldly po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticke as <hi>Achitophel,</hi> whoſe aduice <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. 23.</note> was like as one had asked counſell at the oracle of God; in ciuill pollicie matchable with the children of the Eaſt, the Prieſts of Egypt, the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers of Greece; wiſer then <hi>Ethan,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 4. 30. 31.</note> 
               <hi>Heman, Chalcol</hi> and <hi>Darda,</hi> the ſons of <hi>Mahol;</hi> excelling alſo in wiſdome them of <hi>Tyrus,</hi> which deemed them <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezck.</hi> 28 3.</note> ſelues wiſer then <hi>Daniel:</hi> briefly, though a man were as wiſe as <hi>Salomo,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:3325:13"/>
to whome God gaue prudence and knowledge exceeding much, and a large heart, euen as the ſand that is on the ſea ſhore; ſo that he could ſpeake of beaſts, fowles, creeping things, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 4. 29. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> and of trees, from the Cedar in Lebanon, euen vnto the hyſſope that ſpringeth out of the wall, with the admiration of all that heard him, or heard of him vttering his Prouerbes and Songs by thouſands: Yet ſhall he be counted but vnwiſe in the ſight of God, if againſt the rule of pietie he admit in his hart a pluralitie of gods: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 1. <hi>to the</hi> 18.</note> or bow downe his bodie to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Imagerie: or take the name of the lord his God in vain: or prophane the Lords day: or if contrarie to the rule of charitie contained in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Table of the Decalogue, he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour the parents of his life by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation, or the parents of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie by office, againſt the firſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement: or if he do wrong to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3325:14"/>
his neighbour in his owne perſon, breaking the ſixth Commandement; Thou ſhalt not kill: or in the perſons of thoſe of his familie, tranſgreſſing the ſeuenth Commandement; Thou ſhalt not commit adulterie: or in his goods, violating the eighth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement; Thou ſhalt not ſteale: or in his good name, preiudicing the ninth Commandement; Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe againſt thy neighbour: or if he haue in his mind any lewde cogitation or wandering conceipt, offending againſt the tenth Commaundement; Thou ſhalt not couet thy neighbours houſe, neither ſhalt thou couet thy neighbours wife, nor his man-ſeruant, nor his mayde, nor his oxe, nor his aſſe, nor any thing that is thy neighbours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saule</hi> may thinke himſelfe poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke and wiſe in making ſupplication to the Lord, by offering a burnt offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in Gilgal, when he ſeeth the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3325:14"/>
people ſcattered from him before the battell againſt the Philiſtims: but the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he muſt heare <hi>Samuel</hi> to take him vp <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. 13.</note> roundly, ſaying: Thou haſt done fooliſhly, thou haſt not kept the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of the Lord thy God, which he commaunded thee. And although the Galathians weene well of their owne wiſedome, yet Saint <hi>Paule</hi> telleth them flatly, that they <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 1. 3.</note> are fooliſh, for that after they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne in the Spirite (or the doctrine of the Goſpell) they would now be made perfect in the fleſh (or the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of the Law.)</p>
            <p>But <hi>Dauid</hi> being a man after Gods <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sa.</hi> 13. 14.</note> owne heart, was heauenly wiſe, who could truely make this proteſtation by an <hi>Apoſtrophe</hi> to God, ſaying: Thy teſtimonies haue I taken as an heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 111. 112.</note> for euer: for they are the very ioy of mine heart. I haue applyed my heart to fulfill thy ſtatutes alwayes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto the end. The lawe of thy <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib. verſ.</hi> 72.</note>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:3325:15"/>
mouth is better vnto me, then thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of gold and ſiluer. Thy ſtatutes <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib. verſ.</hi> 54.</note> haue bene my ſongs in the houſe of my pilgrimage. I haue ſeene an end <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib. ver.</hi> 96. <hi>to the</hi> 107.</note> of all perfection, but thy commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement is exceeding large: oh, how loue I thy law? it is my meditation continually. By thy commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments thou haſt made me wiſer then mine enemies: for they are euer with me. I haue had more vnderſtanding then all my teachers: for thy teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies are my meditation. I vnderſtood more then the auncient, becauſe I kept thy precepts. I haue refrained my feete from euery euill way, that I might keepe thy word. I haue not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined from thy iudgements: for thou didſt teach me. How ſweet are thy promiſes vnto my mouth? yea more then hony vnto my mouth. By thy precepts I haue gotten vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, therfore I hate all the waies of falſehood. Thy word is a lanterne
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3325:15"/>
vnto my feete, and a light vnto my path. I haue ſworne and will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it, that I will keepe thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous iudgements. Thus we ought by <hi>Dauids</hi> example to apply our hearts vnto wiſedome.</p>
            <p>Howbeit harkening what is done abroad in the world, I heare of many which badly number their yeares that they may apply their hearts vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to folly, as they did in <hi>Eſaies</hi> time. For when the Prophets put men in mind of their mortalitie, threatning them with haſtie deſtruction, except they would bring foorth ſpeedy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, then the ſenſuall and licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 22. 13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 32.</note> perſons of that age encouraged one another in wickedneſſe, ſaying: Let vs eate and drinke, for to morow we ſhall dy. Tell me ye whoſe eies be open to ſee and marke, how many men do faſhion themſelues &amp; walke <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 2.</note> according to the courſe of this world, and after the Prince that ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3325:16"/>
in the aire, euen the ſpirite that now worketh in the children of diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience; whether there be any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference at all betweene the manner of this age, and his time who penned the booke of Wiſedome, wherein the vngodly reaſon thus: Our life is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>VViſ.</hi> 2.</note> ſhort and tedious, the breath is a ſmoke in our noſthrils<hi>:</hi> our time is as the trace of a cloud driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away with the whirling wind, as a miſt dried vp with the heate of the day, and as a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing ſhadow; neither is there in death any recouerie, nor doth any returne from the graue. Come ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and let vs enioy the pleaſures that are preſent: let not the flower of our youth paſſe by vs; let vs crowne our ſelues with Roſe-buds afore they be withered: let vs leaue ſome toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our pleaſure in euerie place, for that is our portion, and this is our lot: Let vs oppreſſe the poore which is iuſt, eſpecially if he checke vs for
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3325:16"/>
tranſgreſſing the lawe of God: let vs examine him with rebukes and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that we may know his meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and proue his patience: In a word, let our ſtrength be the law of vnrighteouſneſſe. Such things do the vngodly imagine, and go aſtray: for their owne wickedneſſe hath blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them, and they do not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the myſteries of God, neither hope for the reward of righteouſnes, nor can diſcerne the honour of the ſoules that are faultleſſe. Of the crew of ſuch ill numberers of their yeares was the rich Glutton, who applied <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. 19.</note> his heart wholly to intemperancy, labouring all for the backe and the belly: and <hi>Potiphars</hi> wife, who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 39. 7.</note> her heart only to incontinency, for the ſatisfying of her luſts<hi>:</hi> and churliſh <hi>Nabal,</hi> who applied his hart <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. 3. 10. 11.</note> to nought ſauing auarice, for the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of his coffers: and vainglorious <hi>Abſalom,</hi> who applied his heart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3325:17"/>
to ambition by ſeeking ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 1. to the 13.</note> through vnlawfull meanes; ſo that though <hi>Abſaloms</hi> body ſtand at the lower end of the preſence, yet his heart ſitteth iuſt vnder the cloth of eſtate. And likewiſe malitious <hi>Haman,</hi> who applied his hart day and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſther</hi> 3. 6.</note> night to be cruelly reuenged of the whole nation of the Iewes, for the hatred which he bare to one onely good man, namely <hi>Mordecai.</hi> Yea, euen <hi>Iob,</hi> though otherwiſe an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 1. 1.</note> and iuſt man, one that feared God and eſchewed euill, in his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection numbred his yeares naughtily, while in regard of the ſhortneſſe, infirmities, vncertaintie, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.</note> and miſeries of his life he proued im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient, expoſtulating with God, and grudging at the greatneſſe of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions which were layd vpon him. And I obſerue that <hi>Dauid</hi> alſo vpon the like accident, was ouertaken with <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39. 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6.</note> the ſame infirmitie, in the 39 Pſalme.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3325:17"/>
For perceiuing the wicked aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and himſelfe with other godly perſons ſuppreſſed (happily during the conſpiracy of <hi>Abſalom</hi> and his adherents) he grudged againſt God, conſidering the greatneſſe of his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, and the ſhortneſſe of his life, raſhly reaſoning with God as though he were too ſeuere toward his weake creature. And ſomewhat the like ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 84.</note> may be drawne out of the 119 Pſalme, the 84 verſe.</p>
            <p>But the ſame Princely Prophet v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ſounder aduiſe, at another time played the part of a better Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titian in this point of numbring his dayes. For conſidering that he and <note place="margin">1. <hi>Chro.</hi> 29. 12. 14. 15.</note> his Princes were ſtraungers before God, and ſoiourners like their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and that their dayes were like the ſhadow vppon the earth, where there is no long abiding: hereupon he concludeth in his confeſſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the people, that whatſoeuer he
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3325:18"/>
and his Princes had offered toward the future building of the temple, it was but a portion reſtored to God of that which was his owne: and that whatſoeuer riches or honor they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed, they had but the vſe and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupation thereof for a time as tenants at will; for the which they ought to be thankefull during life, and ſhould be anſwerable for the preſent ſtewardſhip or diſpoſing thereof, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iacob</hi> alſo rightly numbred the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 47. 9. 4. 6.</note> dayes of his pilgrimage to be few and euil, while he ſequeſtred himſelfe and his ofspring in the land of Goſhen from the company and cuſtomes of the ſuperſtitious Aegyptians.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Samuel</hi> likewiſe caſt a right ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. 1.</note> of his yeares, who when he was become olde, made his ſonnes Iudges of Iſraell, becauſe he was not able to beare the charge. Semblably, <hi>Eleazarus</hi> one of the principall <note place="margin">2. <hi>Mach.</hi> 6. 23. 24. 25.</note>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:3325:18"/>
Scribes in Iury, would not vnder the perſecution of <hi>Antiochus</hi> for the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his life, diſſemble in a point of Religion, to the hazzard of others by his bad example, becauſe it became not his age, and the excellency of his auncient yeares, and the honour of his gray haires being ninetie yeares olde.</p>
            <p>Moreouer <hi>Polycarpus</hi> the Biſhop <note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. 4. cap. 15.</note> of Smirna, being perſecuted vnder the Emperour <hi>Verus</hi> about the yeare of our Lord 170, made a good audite of his yeares to moue himſelfe to conſtancy. For when the Proconſull of Aſia ſayd vnto him, Spare thine age, I will let thee go if thou wilt ſweare by the fortune of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and raile vpon Chriſt: he made anſwer thus, Theſe 86 yeares haue I ſerued him, and he neuer did me any hurt at all; how then can I reuile, or ſpeake ill of my Sauiour? And the golden mouthed Doctor aduiſed the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3325:19"/>
flocke committed to his charge, to <note place="margin">Chryſoſt. tom. 3. in ſerm. de Euchar.</note> reckon how many houres they found in a weeke, namely 168, that they might out of that number take ſome few at the leaſt to be employed in publike prayer, and hearing the word preached.</p>
            <p>Beſide this, in ciuill policy the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedaemonians <note place="margin">Plut. in Lacon. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitut.</note> renowmed for martial me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, were accuſtomed to decline the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues through three tenſes of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatiue moode. For in their ſolemne aſſemblies, the firſt Chorus was of old men, ſaying: <hi>We were</hi> once <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> renowmed in the wars. In the ſecond rancke marched their luſtie gallants, brauing it, and ſaying: <hi>We are</hi> ſuch men, make triall if you dare. And in the third Pageant came the boyes with great ſigne of militarie towardnes, ſaying: <hi>We ſhall be</hi> one day farre more ſtrong and vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant. And ſurely conſidering the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3325:19"/>
termes wherin we ſtand at this time, it is meet for euery man to fall a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring his yeares, that he may exactly know what place of ſeruice is aſſigned vnto him for the defence of the Realme, according to the Greeke verſe:</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <note place="margin">Ariſtoph. Gram.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Which by ſome hath bene Latined backward thus: <hi>Vota ſenum, conſulta virorum, &amp; facta iuuentae.</hi> As if I ſhould ſay in plaine Engliſh, <hi>Let yong men be valiant in action, let men of middle age be wiſe in conſultation, and let old men be deuout in prayer,</hi> for the good ſucceſſe of the warres either de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue or offenſiue againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon enemies of this Church, and common wealth.</p>
            <p>But commending the war-cauſes to Gods prouidence, the wiſedome of the Councell boord, and the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3325:20"/>
of them that profeſſe Armes, and to ſpeake of manners meete to be exerciſed in the times both of warre and peace; regarding aſwell the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of our yeares paſt, as alſo the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie, frailtie, and vncertainty of the yeares to come: let vs conſider one <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 24.</note> another to prouoke vnto loue, and to good works. We muſt do the works of God, while it is day (that is, while <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9. 4.</note> oportunitie and the ſeaſon ſerueth:) the night commeth when no man can worke. And till the long night of ſleepe do come, from the which there ſhall be no awaking of the body before the trumpet ſhall ſound at the day of iudgement; in the meane while (dearly beloued) I beſeech you <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 11.</note> as ſtraungers and pilgrimes, abſtaine from fleſhly luſts which fight againſt the ſoule. Yea whiles we haue time, let vs do good to all men, but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 10.</note> vnto them which are of the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of faith. And this I ſay (bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren)
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3325:20"/>
becauſe the time is ſhort here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, that both they which haue wiues, be as though they had none: <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor</hi> 7. 29. 30. 31.</note> and they that weepe, as though they wept not: and they that reioyce, as though they reioyced not: and they that buy, as though they poſſeſſed not: and they that vſe this world, as though they vſed it not: for the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of this world goeth away. Wherefore loue not the world, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2. 15. 16. 17.</note> the things that are in the world: as the luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eyes, and the pride of life, which are not of the father, but of the world. And ſurely the world paſſeth away together with the luſts thereof. Alſo conſidering the ſeaſon, it is now time that we ſhould ariſe from ſleepe: for <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 11. 12.</note> now is our ſaluation neerer, then whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we firſt began to beleeue. The night (of ignorance) is paſt, and the day (of the knowledge of God) is come: let vs therefore caſt away the workes of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3325:21"/>
darkneſſe, and let vs put on the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of light (that is, godly and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt maners.) God heareth men in a <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 2.</note> time accepted, in the day of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doth he ſuccour them: behold now the accepted time, behold now the day of ſaluation. The holy Ghoſt ſayth: To day if you will heare his <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 7. 8.</note> voyce harden not your hearts as in the prouocation, according to the day of tentation in the wilderneſſe. Exhort one another while it is called <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib. verſ.</hi> 13.</note> to day, leſt any of you be hardened through the deceiptfulneſſe of ſinne. Boaſt not thy ſelfe of to morow: for <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 27. 1.</note> thou knoweſt not what a day may bring forth. Remember that the rich <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.</note> Glutton once might and would not heare <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets<hi>:</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward he would and could not. The fooliſh virgins which wanted oile in <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 1: <hi>to the</hi> 14.</note> their lampes at the entrance of the bridegroome into the wedding roome, could neuer after that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3325:21"/>
fauour to haue the doores ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto them. And when as <hi>Eſau</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 25. 29. <hi>to the end.</hi>
               </note> had once ſold his birth-right for a meſſe of red pottage, and a morſell of bread; ye know how that afterward alſo when he would haue inherited the bleſſing, he was reiected: For he found no place to repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, though <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 16. 17.</note> he ſought the bleſſing with teares. Wherefore ô Lord, who art the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainer and gouernor of all times and ſeaſons, vouchſafe to teach vs in fit and due time to number our dayes, ſo that we may apply our hearts to wiſedome.</p>
            <p>Children vpon this point of num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring their yeares, may enter into meditation thus: This age of ours is meeteſt to be Catechiſed: that which is now taught, is ſooneſt receiued and longeſt kept. We know what we are to learne by that which is inioyned others to teach vs: for <hi>Moſes</hi> requireth the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 7.</note> Iſraelites, to whet the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3325:22"/>
of the Lord vppon their children (that they might imprint the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more deeply in memory.) And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> commaundeth parents to bring <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 4.</note> vp their children in the inſtruction and information of the Lord. <hi>Daniel</hi> made ſhewe in his childhood what <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 1.</note> he was like to proue in his age, for zeale in religion, honeſty of life, and wiſedome in gouernement. As <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt being a child, grew <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 80.</note> in body, ſo he waxed ſtrong in ſpirit. <hi>Timothie</hi> knew the holy Scriptures of <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 15.</note> a child, and was thereby made wiſe vnto ſaluation. We muſt be dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Lord from our tender age, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. 28.</note> as <hi>Samuel</hi> was. If our ſanctification went before our birth, as in <hi>Ieremy:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 1. 5.</note> our duty is to ſerue God, from the firſt breath to the laſt gaſpe. Yea we are the Seminarie and nurſerie of the Church and common wealth, euen the hope of the future ſtay of them both in time to come. Wherefore
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3325:22"/>
(good Lord) teach vs ſo to number our dayes, that we may apply our hearts vnto wiſedome.</p>
            <p>The young man which is in the prime of his age, and the vigour of his ſtrength, may (in the numbring of his dayes) diſcourſe thus with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: Though I be now young and liuely, freſh and gallant; yet I haue often heard it vttered out of the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, and I beleeue it to be true, That al <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40. 6. 7.</note> fleſh is graſſe which withereth, and all the grace thereof is as the flower of the field which fadeth. This life of mine what is it but an hand breadth, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39. 5. <hi>Iob.</hi> 7. 7. 9. 6.</note> or a ſpanne long? or like the puft of a wind, that paſſeth and commeth not againe? or as a cloude that vaniſheth and goeth away? My dayes are ſwif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. 20.</note> then a weauers ſhittle: they are as a tale that is told: as a dreame when one awaketh. We are but of yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 8. 9.</note> and therefore ignorant in many things: howbeit, for certaintie know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3325:23"/>
this, that our dayes vpon earth are but a ſhadow, or rather as the dreame of a ſhadow. Though loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the glaſſe, I ſee much that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Pind. Pyt. Od.</hi> 8.</note> me, yet I conſider that fauor is deceiptfull, and beautie is vanitie. I thinke my ſelfe now quicke witted: but I may liue till the yeares of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro</hi> 31. 30. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 19. 35.</note> wherein I ſhall not be able to diſcerne betweene good and euill. Though I were deemed now as valo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous as any of <hi>Dauids</hi> Worthies, yet <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.</note> the time will come (if I liue to it) that feare ſhall be in the way. Be it I were <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12. 5. <hi>Iud.</hi> 15. 15.</note> as ſtrong as <hi>Sampſon,</hi> who ſlue a thouſand men with the iaw bone of an aſſe; and carried away the gates of Azzah vpon his ſhoulders, with the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iud.</hi> 16. 3.</note> poſts and barres thereof; and by mayne ſtrength pulled downe a great and ſtrongly built houſe ſtanding v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib. verſ.</hi> 29. 30.</note> pillars, in the ouerthrow where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there periſhed the Princes of the Philiſtims, and others of that vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3325:23"/>
race to the number of three thouſand: yet the brawne of theſe my puiſſant armes will one day fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and the keepers of the houſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12. 3.</note> (that is, the hands which keepe the bodie) ſhall tremble: and more then that, it muſt coſt me my life; or elſe, at length (ere I die) the graſſehop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib. verſ.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſhall be a burden. What if I be now ſharpe ſighted as an eagle? cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely hereafter they that looke out by the windowes (that is, the eyes) will waxe darke, and call for helpe of the ſpectacles. And if I were as ſpeedy on foot as <hi>Aſahel,</hi> who was as ſwift as <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sa.</hi> 2. 18.</note> a wild Roe, yet in the end the ſtrong <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12. 3.</note> men (that is, the legges) will bow, &amp; either leaue to execute their function at all, or elſe be able to performe but a ſnailes pace. Though I now eate &amp; drinke with delight, yet in time to come, the grinders (that is, the teeth) ſhall ceaſe: and the doore (that is, the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib. verſ.</hi> 4.</note> lippes or mouth) ſhall be ſhut with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3325:24"/>
by the baſe ſound of the grin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, when the iawes ſhall ſcarce o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, and not be able to chew any more. The vſe of muſicke ſeemeth now very pleaſant, but one day ſhall al the daughters of ſinging be abaſed: that is, the wind-pipes ſhall not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to do their office, nor the eares be apt to heare the ſound either of voice or of inſtrument: witneſſe the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Barzillai</hi> the Gileadite, who <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 19. 32. 33. 34. 35.</note> being very aged, did for theſe defects refuſe to feede with king <hi>Dauid</hi> at the Court in Ieruſalem. Be it farre from me to let myne heart cheare me in <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 11. 9. 10.</note> the dayes of my youth, and to walke in the wayes of mine heart, and in the ſight of mine eyes, ſeeing that childhood and youth are vanity: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought I to be ignorant, that for all theſe things God will bring me to iudgement. Suppoſe I do now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell in the well proportioned linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the bodie, and rare qualities
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3325:24"/>
of the mind: euen therefore I muſt beſtow theſe excellencies on him who gaue them, glorifying God in my bodie and my ſpirit, becauſe they <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 20.</note> are Gods by a triple right, of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Redemption, and Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Aſſuredly, if I know not God in my youth, he will not acknowledge me in mine age. If I doe not conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate to God the flower of my young yeares, he will ſcorne the dregges of mine elder yeares. How ſhould I thinke to beſtow vpon Sathan the beautie, ſtrength and nimbleneſſe of my youth, in hope that God will be pleaſed with the wrinkles, infirmities and feebleneſſe of my latter age? Wherefore I will now remember my Creator in the dayes of my youth, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12. 1.</note> while the euill dayes come not, nor the yeares approach wherein I ſhall ſay: I haue no pleaſure in them.</p>
            <p>And I am not the firſt that ſhal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne this courſe: for many haue tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3325:25"/>
the ſame path before me: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Moſes,</hi> who from his youth (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 25. 26.</note> that he came to the yeares of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion) abandoned the moment any pleaſures of ſinne, becauſe he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the recompence of an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reward. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> alſo was in his flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 39. 12.</note> yeares when he left his vpper garment in the hands of his maſters wife, who laboured to allure him vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to lewdneſſe. Likewiſe <hi>Ioſiah</hi> entring into the kingdome in the eighth <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chr.</hi> 34. 1. 3. 8. 14. 31. 33.</note> yeare of his raigne, began at 16. years old to ſeeke after the God of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, &amp; in the twentieh yeare of his age he reformed Religion, and in the 26. thereof he repaired the temple: by which occaſion, the booke of the lawe, euen the copie that <hi>Moſes</hi> left, was found in the ruines of it. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon followed a general repentance, and a couenant with the Lord of all hands, and the celebrating of a Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer with ſuch ſolemnitie, as the like
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3325:25"/>
had not bene kept in Iſraell from the <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chr.</hi> 35. 18</note> dayes of <hi>Samuel</hi> the Prophet. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, <hi>Daniel</hi> and his companions <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 1. 4. 5. 8.</note> were both young and paſſing wel-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured without all blemiſh, when they would not defile themſelues with the diet which the Babylonian Emperour had aſſigned vnto them; fearing leſt by that large and daintie fare (as by a ſweet poyſon) they might haue bene drawne to forget their religion, the miſerie of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue countrie, and their accuſtomed temperance. In like ſort <hi>Timothy</hi> kept <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 20</note> that which was committed vnto him, and ſtirred vp the gift of God that <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 6.</note> was in him, in ſuch ſort, that no man could deſpiſe his youth, becauſe he <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 12</note> was vnto them that beleeued, an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſample in word, in conuerſation, in loue, in ſpirit, in faith, in pureneſſe. Now if I get nothing in my youth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 25. 3.</note> (be it in matters ſpirituall or tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall) what ſhall I find in mine age?
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3325:26"/>
Some tell me I am tearmed <hi>Iuuenis à iuuando,</hi> becauſe I ſhould helpe the Church and weale-publike to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt of my power<hi>:</hi> therfore good Lord, to enable me hereunto, teach me to number my dayes, ſo that I may apply my heart vnto wiſedome.</p>
            <p>They that are paſt their ful growth and are come to the ſtanding ſtate of their age, may in numbring their yeares which be ſpent, and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their condition preſent, reaſon thus if it pleaſe them: Howſoeuer we forgot our ſelues in the ignorance of our childhood, and the vanitie of our youth; yet this age of ours requireth other manners. It is ſufficient that we haue beſtowed the time paſſed of the <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet</hi> 4. 3.</note> life, after the faſhion of this world: now it is high time for vs to be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the renewing of our minds, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 2.</note> that we may proue what is the good will of God, and acceptable and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. It was a ſhame for the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:3325:26"/>
that <hi>Paule</hi> could not ſpeake <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 1.</note> vnto them as vnto ſpirituall men, but as vnto carnall, euen as vnto babes in Chriſt. It was in like manner, a great reproch vnto the Hebrewes, for that when as concerning the time they ought to haue bene teachers, yet had they neede againe that the author of that Epiſtle ſhould teach them the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 13. 14.</note> firſt principles of the word of God: and were become ſuch, as had neede of milke, and not of ſtrong meate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are of age, which through long cuſtome haue their wits exerciſed to diſcerne both good and euill. When <hi>Paule</hi> was a child, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 11.</note> he ſpake as a child, he vnderſtood as a child, he thought as a child: but when he became a man, he put away childiſh things. Of vs chiefly it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, that we be alreadie growne vp into him which is the head (that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 15. 13</note> is, Chriſt) vnto a perfect man, &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the meaſure of the age of the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3325:27"/>
of Chriſt. Of vs I ſay it is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that ayming at perfection, we ſhould forget that which is behind, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 13. 14.</note> and indeuour our ſelues vnto that which is before, following hard to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the marke, for the price of the high calling of God in Chriſt Ieſus. It is looked for at our hands, that we be deſeruedly tearmed <hi>Viri à virtute.</hi> So that we ſhould be manfull (when neede is) for the defence of our countrie, wiſe in conſulting, vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in example of life, and euery way the men of God, being abſolute and <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 17.</note> made perfect vnto all good workes which God hath ordained, that we <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 10.</note> ſhould walke in them: not onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying vngodlines and worldly luſts; but alſo liuing ſoberly and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 12. 13</note> and godly in this preſent world; looking for the bleſſed hope and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of the glorie of the mightie God, &amp; of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt. And in the meane time it appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3325:27"/>
vnto vs, as well as vnto others, or rather aboue others, to watch, to <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 13.</note> ſtand faſt in the faith, to quite vs like men, and to be ſtrong in the Lord, and in the power of his might: ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing long ſince put on the whole ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 6 10. 11. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> of God, that we may be able to ſtand faſt againſt all the aſſaults of the diuell; hauing our loynes girded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with veritie, and hauing on the breſt-plate of righteouſneſſe; and our feet being ſhod with the preparation of the Goſpell of peace, &amp;c. praying vnto God for grace, that we may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes put our truſt in him, being ſtrong and conſtant in our vocation; and that he will vouchſafe to ſtabliſh <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31. 24</note> our hearts, and confirme vs with hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly ſtrength vnto the end. Thus good Lord, teach vs to number our dayes, that we may apply our hearts vnto wiſedome.</p>
            <p>Let me now come to the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend age of my moſt deare and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3325:28"/>
dread Soueraign, who hath (I doubt not) learned to number her yeares, that ſhe may apply her hart vnto wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. And therefore I conceiue in mind, that in her <hi>ſoliloquia</hi> or priuate meditations, ſhe frameth her ſpeech in this wiſe:</p>
            <p>Remember not the ſinnes of my <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25. 7.</note> youth, nor my tranſgreſſions: but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy kindneſſe remember me, euen for thy goodneſſe ſake, ô Lord. Behold, I was borne in iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 5.</note> and in ſinne hath my mother co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued me. I know mine iniquitie, and my ſinnes are euer before me. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib. ver.</hi> 3.</note> Wherefore leſt the Zion and Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, <note place="margin">18.</note> that is, the Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth of England, ſhould be in daunger of thy wrath, through my former ſinnes: Waſh me thoroughly <note place="margin">2.</note> from mine iniquitie, and cleanſe me from my ſinne: purge me, and I ſhall be cleane: waſh me, and I ſhall be <note place="margin">7.</note> whiter then ſnow.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:3325:28"/>
Lord I know and confeſſe, that in my predeceſſors dayes, and in the 37 yeares paſt of my raigne, thou haſt deliuered me as wonderfully from all my malicious and daungerous ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as thou didſt deliuer thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant <hi>Dauid</hi> from the tyrannie of <hi>Saul</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> and his adherents: from the inuaſion of forraine aduerſaries, as the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtims, <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.</note> Ammonites, Moabites, Idu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maeans, Syrians, &amp;c. and from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward inſurrections, firſt of <hi>Abſalom,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib.</hi> 15. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> and then of <hi>Sheba</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chri;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib.</hi> 20.</note> beſides many other traiterours complots and trecherous conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. Therefore I will alway giue <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. 1.</note> thankes vnto thee ô Lord; thy praiſe ſhal be in my mouth continually. My <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. 1. 2.</note> ſoule praiſe thou the Lord, and all that is within me praiſe his holy name: my ſoule praiſe thou the Lord and forget not all his benefits.</p>
            <p>O Lord, I am now entred a good way into the Climactericall yeare of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3325:29"/>
mine age, which mine enemies wiſh &amp; hope to be fatall vnto me. But thou Lord, which by thy Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 10. 2.</note> commandedſt the houſe of Iſraell not to learne the way of the heathen, nor to be afraid of the ſignes of heauen; and who by thy mighty hand and out-ſtretched arme madeſt the yeare of the greateſt expectation, euen 88. maruellous by the ouerthrowe of thine and mine enemies: Now for thy Goſpels ſake, which hath long had a ſanctuarie in this Iland, make likewiſe 96. as proſperous vnto me and my loyall ſubiects: that by the happie bringing about of this yeare, I may ſtill ſet vp the banner in thy <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 20. 5.</note> name, which art my ſtrength, my <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18. 1. 2</note> rocke, my fortreſſe, my deliuerer, the lifter vp of mine head, my ſhield, the horne alſo of my ſaluation, &amp; my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge. Thou art my hope, ô Lord God, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71. 5. 6.</note> euen my truſt from my youth: vpon thee haue I bene ſtayed from the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:3325:29"/>
wombe: thou art he that tooke me <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib.</hi> 9.</note> out of my mothers bowels: caſt me not off in the time of age, forſake me not when my ſtrength faileth. O for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 138. 8.</note> not me the worke of thine hands, vntill I haue declared thine arme to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71. 18.</note> this generation, and thy power to all them that ſhall come.</p>
            <p>Lord, I haue now put foote within the doores of that age, in the which the Almond tree flouriſheth: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12. 1</note> men begin to cary a Calender in their bones, the ſenſes begin to faile, the ſtrength to diminiſh, yea all the powers of the body daily to decay<hi>:</hi> Now therefore graunt grace, that though mine outward man thus pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh: <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 16.</note> yet mine inward man may be renewed daily. So direct me with thine holy ſpirite, that I may daily waxe elder in godlineſſe; wiſedome <note place="margin">
                  <hi>VViſ.</hi> 4. 9.</note> being my gray haires, and an vndefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led life mine old age. Let thy ſtatutes <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 54.</note> be my ſongs in the houſe of my pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage:
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:3325:30"/>
Sweeter vnto me the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hony <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 10.</note> &amp; the hony-combe vnto my mouth; and more deſired by me then thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1 19. 22.</note> of ſiluer, or the gold of Ophir, yea the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pearle or pretious ſtones. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 8. 11. 19.</note> For though I haue out-liued almoſt all the Nobles of this Realme whom I found poſſeſſed of Dukedome, Marquiſats, Earledoms &amp; Barronries at mine entring into the Kingdome: and likewiſe all the Iudges of the land, and all the Biſhops ſet vp by me after my comming to the Crowne<hi>:</hi> And although I haue ſeene an end of ſundry of theſe once or twiſe ouer: yet what auaileth this my long tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall life in ſuruiuing others, vnleſſe I my ſelfe lead alwayes a ſpirituall life while I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth, in hope to enioy an eternal life whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I am dead?</p>
            <p>And though (Lord) I haue liued in reſpect of my ſelf long inough in this valley of miſerie; ſo that in regard of troubles paſt, and dangers future, I
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3325:30"/>
ſee ſome reaſon to ſay with <hi>Elias:</hi> It is <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 19. 4</note> inough, ô Lord, take my ſoule, for I am no better then my fathers; and with <hi>Paul:</hi> I deſire to be looſed, and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 23.</note> to be with Chriſt: yet becauſe this people reckon of me, as <hi>Dauids</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects did of him, whom they termed <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 21. 17.</note> the light of Iſraell; and for that they eſteeme of me, as the Iewes did of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias,</hi> whom they called the breath of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 4. 20.</note> their noſthrils: Therefore for their ſakes (if it be thy pleaſure in thine hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly prouidence) let me their candle burne yet a while longer; and let me breathe ſtill among them, vntil I haue met with da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers preſent, or immine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and eſtabliſhed the ſtate for the time to come: ſo that not onely peace and <note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 20. 19.</note> truth may be in my dayes; but alſo that after my departure out of this life, they may in the future age, liue in peace and plentie in euery quarter and corner of the Realme, from Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke to Porchmouth, and from the
<pb facs="tcp:3325:31"/>
Margets to the Mount; like as Iſraell and Iudah dwelt without feare, euery <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 4. 25.</note> man vnder his vine, and vnder his fig-tree, from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Beer-ſheba,</hi> all the dayes of <hi>Salomon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if Lord, for the effecting ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of thou meaneſt to deale with me as with <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> by adding to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 20. 6</note> part of my life the terme of 15. yeares more (or rather two fifteenes if it be thy will:) then aſſiſt me euer with thy grace, that during all that time I may know how to go out and <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 3. 7.</note> in: feeding this people according to the ſimplicity of mine heart, and gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78. 72.</note> them by the diſcretion of my hands: That ſo at length I may go to the ſepulchers of my fathers in a good time, as a ricke of corne that is ripe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 5. 26.</note> caried into the barne; yeelding the ſpirite like <hi>Dauid</hi> in a good age full of <note place="margin">1. <hi>Chro.</hi> 29. 28.</note> dayes, riches and honour. And ſo the duſt of this body returning to the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12. 7.</note> earth as it was, my ſpirit may returne
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:3325:31"/>
to thee that gaue it: to enioy alwaies <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. 11.</note> thy preſence, in the which there is fulneſſe of ioy, and to be alwayes at thy right hand, where be pleaſures for euer more; purchaſed and prepared for all them that feare thee, by the mediation of our Lord and Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus. To whom with thee and the holy Ghoſt, be all honour and glory, both now and for euer.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Erratum.</head>
            <p>Pag. 21. lin. 23. <hi>for</hi> firſt <hi>reade</hi> fift.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
